Now that we created our account here and we learned that we'll use git, the next step is on heroku to use
its cli, its command line interface and that of course now is heroku specific. On other hosting providers,
you might simply be able to drag and drop your code, let's say as a zip file into some part of the dashboard
user interface of your hosting provider to deploy it.
heroku just doesn't use such a drag and drop alternative, instead
heroku uses that command line interface which allows you to run your code or to deploy your code through
the command line by typing on commands.
So let's download heroku cli here,
make sure to follow the instructions on the page that opens in case you're facing any problems, here
you also get informed that you require git
so definitely make sure to check that out as well if you have problems.
Now I'll go with my MacOS version there and then I will quickly walk through the installer there and install
heroku on my system.
Once you did install it, the next step is to run this command and you run this in your normal terminal
or command prompt,
I'm here in my code, in my node project but you can run it from anywhere
and there I will type heroku login,
this should now work and you can now login with your account data,
so with the same data you used to login on the website. Now once you did login the next step is to turn
your codebase,
so your project you have been working on into a git repository so that you can add heroku as a remote git
repository and deploy to it,
you can do that with these commands here. Now
I already have a git repository here so I will omit the git init command and I will just use heroku
git remote -a and then the name of my project and this will essentially add it as a remote project
and also set my remote project url as a remote repository on this local codebase
because this then allows me to run these commands to create a new commit, a new so-called snapshot which
you need and then this push command to push my code to heroku.
Now I set heroku as a remote branch,
next in your package.json file of your project, you want to add a new entry, the engines entry
anywhere maybe above the scripts and there add node and now set the version of
nodejs you are using.
You can detect that by running node -v in your project folder or anywhere on your computer actually and
you see for me it's 10.9.0,
you might be using a different version, simply enter it here and this will now use that version when
it installs that on that remote server
we are going to deploy it to. Now
additionally in app.js, for heroku you may want to make sure you are using compression because heroku
does not offer you to set up compression on the fly, other hosting providers do that,
this one does not do it so do it on your own.
Also make sure that you are not trying to read in our certificate and private key here for SSL, so comment
that out because these files will not be deployed because we'll not use SSL
here, you should not be spinning up your own https server because we will do that through heroku's managed
server or you would do it through heroku's managed server, so spinup a normal http server instead.
Now with that changed,
make sure that you also add a new file and that is heroku specific,
the procfile without a file extension and there, you simply add web:node app.js
and this will instruct heroku to execute your app.js file when it tries to run your application.
Now for different hosting providers, this might differ of course and there you simply have to check their
documentation to find out how you'll let them know which script or which command they should execute
to run your app. With all that set up,
make sure you add a
.gitignore file because this will tell git which folders
it should not actually include in its snapshots and there, the node modules folder is important, all your
third party packages are stored there and we won't deploy that
because that will just increase the size of data we have to transmit over the wire,
instead this will automatically be recreated on heroku because heroku and that is the case for all
hosting providers pretty much do install your dependencies on the server after you deploy your code
because keep in mind that in the package.json,
we of course have a list of all the third party packages we're using and the versions we need.
So this will be taken by the hosting provider and it will install all these packages on the server then
ad that is why we always used npm install --save because that added such entries to the package.json
file
which now can be used during deployment. With all that added, create a new snapshot by typing git add .
and then git commit -m and there any message you want between double quotation marks and I will
simply type prepare it for deployment,
close that and hit enter
and now you simply run git push heroku master and you hit enter and this will now upload all your code
to heroku and there also as you see, install all your dependencies,
that is what it's doing now and it should automatically detect that it's a node application because
you have a package.json file,
so you should not be getting any errors here and it will now step by step
spin up your server and install the dependencies and so on.
Now with that, you can go back to your dashboard and click on overview there and you should see that succeeded
build and you can now click on open app.
This will open your app in a new tab and most likely, this will not really succeed
and the reason for that is that we deployed our application but now if you type heroku
logs in your terminal, you will see what went wrong
and to be precise in the error message, you will see that it failed to connect to the database and that
makes sense because all our node environment variables which we rely on, for example to connect to the
database are now not set anymore because in the procfile, we instruct heroku to just execute the app.js
file
and this will not pass the environment variables, only one environment variable is passed by default
by heroku and that is actually node
env, this will be set to production,
that is something they do for you but all the other environment variables are not set.
Now we have to do that on our own by simply grabbing these names and going back to our dashboard and there
on the dashboard, so
you want to go to settings for your app and then go to config vars and there you can now add your
own config vars which are essentially the environment variables that are passed into your application.
You simply add them here step by step as key value pairs,
so all the data we previously passed in as part of our start script, we now pass it here as environment
variables, mongo user, mongo password, also of course the default database,
let's add it here,
that was shop and also the stripe key where you should use your production ready stripe key of course
as you learned, not the testing key necessarily, now if you click add, this is added too
and now we have all these environment variables added here. Now this alone won't do the trick though,
we also need to change something on our mongodb set up in our case here because we are using
that hosted mongodb atlas solution if you remember
and that of course now depends on the database you are using and there, you have to remember that under
security, you had to whitelist IPs which are allowed to connect,
now you need to whitelist the IP of your running application.
And the thing about heroku and its basic version here is that we don't have a static IP assigned to our
project,
instead it's a dynamic range.
Now attached you find some resources that help you, for example assign a static IP. If you have such a
range,
we only can do one thing on add IP address,
we can allow access from anywhere,
keep in mind we are still secure by username and password but still for a better set up, I would recommend
that you also ensure that you assign a static IP.
As I mentioned, you'll find some helpful resources on that attached to this lecture or depending on
your hosting provider,
you might be using a hosting provider that gives you a single ID anyways.
Running mongodb on the same server as your web project is not really an alternative because a
database server is also not very trivial to set up especially if it should be able to scale and so on.
Now with that changed, go back to your overview dashboard of your app and restart your server there by
going to more restart all dynos, a dyno is essentially that
virtual server and thereafter let's try reloading our application here and now there, you should
see a running app.
You should of course also be able to login and all that fun stuff,
so essentially you should be able to interact with it just as you were able to do with it locally
but now it's running remotely
and as you can see, it's automatically served via https.
Now on heroku in case you want to stick to that hosting provider, you can also change things,
you can use your own domain, your own SSL certificate and all that fun stuff
but this is it for now,
this is the essential setup I want to show you here.